{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "The air transport industry was nationalized in the year",
            "optionA": "  1953 ",
            "optionB": "  1950 ",
            "optionC": "  1948 ",
            "optionD": "  1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe air transport industry was nationalized in the year 1953. Indian Airlines and Air India International started operations which were set up under the Air Corporations Act, 1953 after the government nationalised all the airlines of the country. ",
            "keyString": "601549s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following places are known for paper manufacturing industry?\n1. Yamunanagu\n2. Guwahati\n3. Shahabad\n4. Ballarpur",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 2 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 3 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYamunanagu, Guwahati and Ballarpur are known for paper manufacturing industry. ",
            "keyString": "601584s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs is not correctly matched? Important Location (Industry / Mining) : State",
            "optionA": "  Himgir : Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Koraput : Orissa ",
            "optionC": "  Palana : Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Nellore : Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHimgiri Rampur is a Coal Mine (Orissa) in India owned by Coal India.",
            "keyString": "601609s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Put in chronological order the origin of the following industries in India :\nI. Jute\nII. Cotton Textile\nIII. Steel\nIV. Cement",
            "optionA": "  I, II, IV, III ",
            "optionB": "  II, I, III, IV ",
            "optionC": "  II, I, IV, III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II, III, IV ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe chronological order in the origin of the following industries in India are Cotton Textile, Jute, Steel and Cement. ",
            "keyString": "601624s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chhota Nagpur plateau is called the heart of industrial India because it is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Near to major iron and steel centres ",
            "optionB": "  A big link of roads and railways ",
            "optionC": "  Rich in minerals and power fuels ",
            "optionD": "  Very fertile for industrial crops ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChhota Nagpur plateau is called the heart of industrial India because it is rich in minerals and power fuels. ",
            "keyString": "601640s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is not a raw silk producing state?",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBihar is not a raw silk producing state. Bihar accounts for 71% of India's annual litchi production. ",
            "keyString": "651628s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the major rubber producing state in India?",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Odisha ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKerala is the major rubber producing states in India. Kerala accounts for more than 90 per cent of the total rubber production in the country. The total area under rubber cultivation in the state is 5.45 lakh hectares. Rest of the natural rubber is produced in Tamil Nadu and North East states. ",
            "keyString": "651669s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which states is the biggest producer of cashewnut?",
            "optionA": "  Mharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt may be observed that Maharashtra (1.86 lakh ha) was the leading producer of cashew nut followed by Andhra Pradesh (1.85 lakh ha), Odissa (1.82 lakh ha), Karnataka (1.26 lakh ha) and Kerala (0.87 lakh ha). India produces 7.79 lakh MT of cashew nut spread across more than 6 states. ",
            "keyString": "651691s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following is a correct sequence of production of coal in the Indian States in descending order ?",
            "optionA": "  Jharkhand - Madhya Pradesh - West Bengal - Meghalaya ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal - Madhya Pradesh - Jharkhand - Meghalaya ",
            "optionC": "  Jharkhand - West Bengal - Meghalaya - Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh - Jharkhand - West Bengal - Meghalaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJharkhand - Madhya Pradesh - West Bengal - Meghalaya is a correct sequence of production of coal in the Indian States in descending order. ",
            "keyString": "651708s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The State in India which produces the largest quantity of common salt is",
            "optionA": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe State in India which produces the largest quantity of common salt is Gujarat. Gujarat is the largest salt producer state of India and third largest in the world. The state contributes 76% to the total salt production in India, Kharaghoda, Bhavnagar, Porbandar and Rann of Kutch of Gujarat are major salt produced districts. ",
            "keyString": "651726s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest producer of Lac in India is",
            "optionA": "  Chattisgarh ",
            "optionB": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLac is resinous secretion of wide range of lac insects.Most common species is Kerria lacca utilized for lac production. In India, Jharkhand is the leading producer of lac followed by Chattisgarh, West Bengal & Maharashtra. It is used to make dyes & bangles, filling of hollow silver and gold ornaments. ",
            "keyString": "702919s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The only State which produces saffron in the Indian Union is",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionD": "  Sikkim ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJammu and Kashmir is the only state in India produce saffron. ",
            "keyString": "702964s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Penicillin is produced at",
            "optionA": "  Bengaluru ",
            "optionB": "  Alwaye ",
            "optionC": "  Poona ",
            "optionD": "  Pimpri ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPenicillin is produced at Pimpri. Penicillin, one of the first and still one of the most widely used antibiotic agents, derived from the Penicillium mold. The naturally occurring penicillins, penicillin G (benzylpenicillin) and penicillin V (phenoxymethylpenicillin), are still used clinically. ",
            "keyString": "702986s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following States of India is the largest producer of lignite coal?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTamil Nadu is the largest producer of lignite coal. Lignite coal is obtained from Gujarat & Tamil Nadu in India.",
            "keyString": "703003s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a major sugarcane-producing state in India?",
            "optionA": "  Odisha ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaharashtra is a major sugarcane-producing state in India. Maharashtra's sugar production has already crossed 10 million tonnes. ",
            "keyString": "703019s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following neighbouring country of India is the largest producer of Opium in the World?",
            "optionA": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionB": "  Afghanistan ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "optionD": "  Maldives ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfghanistan is largest opium producer of word and is part of Golden crescent which includes Pakistan and Afghanistan both. ",
            "keyString": "769233s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a plant product?",
            "optionA": "  Camphor ",
            "optionB": "  Aloe vera ",
            "optionC": "  Vanilla ",
            "optionD": "  All are plant products ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCamphor, Aloe vera and Vanilla all the three are plant product. ",
            "keyString": "769264s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the realm of coal production in the world, India ranks ________ ",
            "optionA": "  First ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  Third ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the realm of coal production in the world, India ranks fourth. ",
            "keyString": "769277s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Major producer of mulberry silk in India is",
            "optionA": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMajor producer of mulberry silk in India is Karnataka. Karnataka is the largest producer of silk in India. The state produces an average of around 8,200 metric tonnes of silk every year, which is about one-third of the total silk production in India. Up to November 2017, Karnataka has produced 5,962 metric tonnes of silk, which is about one-third of the Indian silk production. Mysuru and North Bengaluru in Karnataka are famous for their silks and are called the \u201cSilk City\u201d as they majorly contribute to the silk production in India. ",
            "keyString": "769290s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following products has Bangladesh emerged as the main competitor of India in the world market?",
            "optionA": "  Cement ",
            "optionB": "  Cotton garments ",
            "optionC": "  Jute ",
            "optionD": "  Pharmaceuticals ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn production of jute, Bangladesh emerged as the main competitor of India in the world market. Newly started jute industry in Bangladesh has captured some of the market of Indian jute goods. ",
            "keyString": "769302s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The chief coal bearing formation in India is known as the",
            "optionA": "  Siwaliks ",
            "optionB": "  Gondwanas ",
            "optionC": "  Vindhyans ",
            "optionD": "  Cuddappahs ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe chief coal bearing formation in India is known as the Gondwanas. Gondwana rocks contain nearly 98% of India's coal reserves. The Gondwana coals of Permian times are mainly found in the Peninsular Gondwana basins of India. ",
            "keyString": "868636s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The First refinery in India was established in",
            "optionA": "  Barauni ",
            "optionB": "  Vishakhapatnam ",
            "optionC": "  Digboi ",
            "optionD": "  Mumbai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOldest working petroleum refinery is in Digboi, Assam.It was started in the year 1901 by British. It was infact first oil well drilled in Asia. It is also known as 'Oil City'. ",
            "keyString": "868852s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following hydroelectric projects does not belog to Tamil Nadu?",
            "optionA": "  Idukki ",
            "optionB": "  Aliyar ",
            "optionC": "  Periyar ",
            "optionD": "  Kundah ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIdukki dam is constructed on the river Periyar in Kerala. It is constructed between Kuravan and Kuravathi. With an height of about 168m it is counted among the highest arch dams. ",
            "keyString": "869027s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Critical criteria for the location of an aluminium plant in India are the availability of bauxite and ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Electricity ",
            "optionC": "  Labour ",
            "optionD": "  Ready market ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCritical criteria for the location of an aluminium plant in India are the availability of bauxite and electricity. ",
            "keyString": "869191s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following States, which one has the highest amount of Nickel Ore resources?",
            "optionA": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionB": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrissa has the highest amount of Nickel Ore resources. Odisha's resources of Bauxite, Chromite, Coal, Iron ore, Manganese and Nickel ore are formidable constituting approx.50%, 98%, 25%, 35%, 27% and 91% respectively of the total resources of the country. ",
            "keyString": "869345s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following hydro-electric stations is situated in Uttar Pradesh?",
            "optionA": "  Mayurakshi ",
            "optionB": "  Rihand ",
            "optionC": "  Kangsabati ",
            "optionD": "  Hirakud ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRihand hydro-electric stations is situated in Uttar Pradesh. Rihand Dam is the largest multi-purpose project of Uttar Pradesh (UP), India. The dam was constructed on the river Rihand (Tributary of the Son River) near village Pipri in Sonbhadra district of UP. ",
            "keyString": "952020s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Huge deposit of uranium are found recently in",
            "optionA": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Kanrataka ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTummalapalle of Andhra Pradesh has one of the largest uranium reserves of the world. This report was concluded by Atomic Energy Commission of India after condueting the research in 2011. ",
            "keyString": "953051s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jadugoda is famous for?",
            "optionA": "  Mining of iron ",
            "optionB": "  Mining of mica ",
            "optionC": "  Mining of uranium ",
            "optionD": "  Mining of copper ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJadugoda is the village in Purbi Singhbhum district of Jharkhand state. It was first uranium mine of India operationalised in 1967. ",
            "keyString": "953582s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Khetri is famous for",
            "optionA": "  Aluminium ",
            "optionB": "  Fertilizers ",
            "optionC": "  Copper ",
            "optionD": "  Gold ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhetri in Rajasthan is very well known for copper.It is the town in Jhunjhunu distric. ",
            "keyString": "954027s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are correct?\n1. Broad guage railway engines - Varanasi\n2. Electric locomotives - Bhopal\n3. Integral Coach Factory - Kolkata",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tElectric locomotives - Bhopal is the correct option. ",
            "keyString": "954490s17m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following lists four type of coal, arranged in the increasing order of their carbon content?",
            "optionA": "  Peat, Lignite, Bituminous, Anthracite ",
            "optionB": "  Peat, Bituminous, Lignite, Anthracite ",
            "optionC": "  Lignite, Peat, Bituminous, Anthracite ",
            "optionD": "  Peat, Anthracite, Lignite, Bituminous ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFour type of coal, arranged in the increasing order of their carbon content are Peat, Lignite, Bituminous and Anthracite. ",
            "keyString": "41493s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oldest oil-field in India is in",
            "optionA": "  Haldia ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay High ",
            "optionC": "  Neyveli ",
            "optionD": "  Digboi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe oldest oil field in India is in Digboi, Assam. In the year 1901, Britishers had set the oil refinery in this region naming it as Assam Oil Company Limited. ",
            "keyString": "42097s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The atomic power station in Rajasthan is situated at",
            "optionA": "  Pokhran ",
            "optionB": "  Suratgarh ",
            "optionC": "  Rawatbhata ",
            "optionD": "  Chittorgarh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe atomic power station in Rajasthan is situated in Rawatbhata. It is also known as Rajasthan Atomic Power Station. It was commissioned on 16th December 1973 & is operated by Nuclear Power Corporationd of India Limited. ",
            "keyString": "42661s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which State of India is leading in solar energy generation?",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Haryana ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRecently, Tamil Nadu surpassed Rajasthan to become number one producer of solar energy. A 648 MW plant of solar energy is set up in Kamuthi, Tamil Nadu by Adani Power. It is world's second largest solar park.",
            "keyString": "43236s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following barrages supplies water to the Indira Gandhi Canal?",
            "optionA": "  Bhakra ",
            "optionB": "  Harika ",
            "optionC": "  Narora ",
            "optionD": "  Pandoh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarika barrages supplies water to the Indira Gandhi Canal. The Indira Gandhi Canal irrigates a vast amount of land in the Indian portion of the Thar. The canal begins at the Harike Barrage at the confluence of the Sutlej and Beas rivers in the Indian Punjab and continues in a southwesterly direction for some 290 miles (470 km). ",
            "keyString": "43814s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the largest producer of lignite in India?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLignite coal is obtained from Gujarat & Tamil Nadu in India. Neyveli which is located in South Arcol district of Tamil Nadu is largest mine of lignite coal. It supplies fuel to thermal power stations in Tamil Nadu. ",
            "keyString": "136872s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following states is a Ieading producer of woollen textiles?",
            "optionA": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPunjab is a Ieading producer of woollen textiles. Punjab is the largest producer of woollen textiles because: Raw material is easily available as sheep rearing is the main occupation in hilly areas adjoining Punjab. Demand for product is high because of very cold winters. ",
            "keyString": "137124s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following States produces the maximum manganese in India?",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadhya Pradesh produces maximum manganese in India. M.P. along with Maharashtra produces more than half of manganese in India.",
            "keyString": "137318s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian city famous for glass bangle industry is",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Sikandrabad ",
            "optionC": "  Firozabad ",
            "optionD": "  Agra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian city famous for glass bangle industry is Firozabad. Firozabad is a city in India, in the state of Uttar Pradesh also known as the City of Glass specially Bangles and so called Suhag Nagari.",
            "keyString": "137497s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "HMT industries are set up at",
            "optionA": "  Kalamassery ",
            "optionB": "  Hyderabad and Bengaluru ",
            "optionC": "  Pinjore and Ajmer ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHMT industries are set up at Kalamassery, Hyderabad and Bengaluru and Pinjore and Ajmer. ",
            "keyString": "137664s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following does not have a unit of Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd (HAL)?",
            "optionA": "  Nasik ",
            "optionB": "  Koraput ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Bangalore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKolkata does not have a unit of Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd (HAL). ",
            "keyString": "233319s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main hydroelectric power potential of the Indus river system lies in India and not in Pakistan because",
            "optionA": "  The need for hydroelectric power is greater in India than the Pakistan ",
            "optionB": "  India has superior technology to develop hydroelectric power ",
            "optionC": "  India has a greater labour force to develop hydroelectric power ",
            "optionD": "  The mountain stages of these rivers lie in India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main hydroelectric power potential of the Indus river system lies in India and not in Pakistan because the mountain stages of these rivers lie in India. Indus is one of the longest rivers of the world and runs for 3,200 kms. It originates in the southwestern Tibet Autonomous Region of China at an elevation of about 18,000 feet. Of the total length, it flows for around 300 kms in India. ",
            "keyString": "233927s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which one of the following industries is Coimbatore associated?",
            "optionA": "  Gold ",
            "optionB": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionC": "  Cotton Textile ",
            "optionD": "  Sericulture ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoimbatore is associated with Cotton Textile industries. Coimbatore houses a large number of small, medium and large textile mills, along with a number of textile research institutes. The city also houses two of the Centers Of Excellences (COE) for technical textiles proposed by Government of India, namely Meditech, a medical textile research centre based at SITRA, and InduTech based in PSG College of Engineering and Technology. ",
            "keyString": "234446s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which industry provides jobs to the maximum number of people?",
            "optionA": "  Iron textiles ",
            "optionB": "  Cotton textiles ",
            "optionC": "  Sugar industry ",
            "optionD": "  Tea processing ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCotton textiles industry provides jobs to the maximum number of people. It has created more 35 lakh job opportunities. ",
            "keyString": "234945s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hindustan Machine Tools has its factories at",
            "optionA": "  Bengaluru (Karnataka) ",
            "optionB": "  Kalamassery (Kerala) ",
            "optionC": "  Pinjore (Haryana) ",
            "optionD": "  All the three places above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHindustan Machine Tools has its factories at Bengaluru (Karnataka), Kalamassery (Kerala) and Pinjore (Haryana). ",
            "keyString": "235419s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A Hydro Power Project on Lake Loktak is situated in which state",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Manipur ",
            "optionC": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionD": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLake Loktak is situated in Manipur. Loktak Hydroelectric, Power Plant constructed on it is owned by NHPC Ltd.",
            "keyString": "338887s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a wrong combination of location and hydroelectric projects undertaken by the NHPC?",
            "optionA": "  Baira Siul-Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Salal-Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Loktak-Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Devi Ghat-Nepal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLoktak Power Station (3 x 35 MW) is a multipurpose storage scheme to harness the hydro power potential of Loktak lake fed by Khuga and Imphal river. ",
            "keyString": "339350s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following substances are found in the beach sands of many parts of Kerala?\n1. Ilmenite\n2. Zircon\n3. Silimanite\n4. Tungsten",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  3 and 4 only ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIlmenite, Zircon and Silimanite are found in the beach sands of many parts of Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "339799s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following region is most rich in coal deposits?",
            "optionA": "  Bramhaputra Valley ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar Valley ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi Valley ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari Valley ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDamodar Valley lies in the Chhota Nagpur region. If has massive blocks of coal fields in its central basin. It also termed as 'Ruhr of India'. ",
            "keyString": "340247s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The thermal power plant of Bokaro is located in",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionC": "  Jharkand ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe thermal power plant of Bokaro is located in Jharkand. Bokaro Thermal Power Station B is located at Bokaro district in Jharkhand, 44 km from the Bokaro Steel City and is about 55 km from Dhanbad city. The nearest railway station is Bokaro Thermal. ",
            "keyString": "340702s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which one of the following districts, have large reserves of diamond-bearing kimberlite been discovered in the recent past?",
            "optionA": "  Hoshangabad ",
            "optionB": "  Raipur ",
            "optionC": "  Sambalpur ",
            "optionD": "  Warangal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Raipur large reserves of diamond-bearing kimberlite been discovered in the recent past. Diamonds in Chattisgarh region of Madhya Pradesh. The presence of pyrope, ilmenite and chromediopside in the Payalikhand gravel has provided positive evidence for the close proximity of diamond bearing kimberlite or lamproite rocks in the area. ",
            "keyString": "426093s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Kowada Nuclear Park project is proposed to be setup in which State?",
            "optionA": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is a proposal to setup Kowada Nuclear Park in Srikakulam district of Andhra Pradesh. It would be jointly developed under Indo-U.S.A. nuclear agreement. ",
            "keyString": "427142s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Raniganj in West Bengal is concerned with",
            "optionA": "  Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Iron are ",
            "optionC": "  Manganese ",
            "optionD": "  Copper ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaniganj coal field is located in Durgapur & Asansol sub divisions of Paschim Bardhaman district of West Bengal. This coal belt stretches to neighbouring state of Jharkhand. ",
            "keyString": "428108s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The major thermal power station fed on natural gas is at",
            "optionA": "  Lunej ",
            "optionB": "  Trombay ",
            "optionC": "  Naharkatiya ",
            "optionD": "  Digboi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe major thermal power station fed on natural gas is at Naharkatiya. It is well known for petroleum and gas reserves. Earlier, Duliajan, the head office town of Oil India Limited was in its circle. ",
            "keyString": "428653s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following cities:\n1. Bhatinda\n2. Jamnagar\n3. Mangalore\nWhich of the above has/have oil refineries?",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  3 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJamnagar and Mangalore have oil refineries. Jamnagar have a total capacity of 1.24 million bpd, making these the world's largest combined oil refining facility. Mangalore Refinery and Petrochemicals Limited (MRPL), is an oil refinery at Mangalore and is a subsidiary of ONGC, set up in 1988. The refinery is located at Katipalla, north from centre of Mangalore city. The refinery was established after displacing five villages of Bala, Kalavar, Kuthetoor, Katipalla, and Adyapadi. ",
            "keyString": "429185s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Highest percentage of carbon is found in which form of coal?",
            "optionA": "  Anthracite ",
            "optionB": "  Bituminous ",
            "optionC": "  Peat ",
            "optionD": "  Lignite ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbout 90% of carbon content is available in anthracite due to which it has low ash & smoke formations. It is best coal available for metallurgical process.",
            "keyString": "507637s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first oil well in India was dug at ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Bombay High ",
            "optionB": "  Moran ",
            "optionC": "  Digboi ",
            "optionD": "  Naharkatiya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first oil well in India was dug at Digboi. Crude oil was discovered here in late 19th century. Digboi is known as the Oil City of Assam where the first oil well in Asia was drilled. The first refinery was started here as early as 1901. Digboi has the oldest oil well in operation. ",
            "keyString": "508719s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the MIG engine manufactured in India?",
            "optionA": "  Koraput ",
            "optionB": "  Bengaluru ",
            "optionC": "  Ozar ",
            "optionD": "  Hyderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMIG engine is manufactured in India in Koraput. Engine Division, koraput was established in the year 1964 to manufacture R11F2-300 Sr III engines for fitment in MiG-21FL Aircraft under licence from erstwhile USSR. In 1976 facilities were established to manufacture R25 engines for fitment in MiG-21BIS aircraft. ",
            "keyString": "509163s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which one of the following places electricity generated from hydel power?",
            "optionA": "  Neyveli ",
            "optionB": "  Ennore ",
            "optionC": "  Tuticorin ",
            "optionD": "  Mettur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tElectricity is generated from hydel power in Mettur. It has thermal and hydroelectric power stations. The 840-megawatt thermal power station acts as one of the base load power plants for Tamil Nadu Electricity Board. ",
            "keyString": "509584s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Natural gas is found in Dharwar rock\nformation ",
            "optionB": "  Mica is found in Koderma ",
            "optionC": "  Cuddapah series is famous for diamonds ",
            "optionD": "  Petroleum reserves are found in Aravali hills ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKoderma is a mineral rich district. It's located in Southern Jharkhand and termed as Great Mica Belt of Jharkhand. ",
            "keyString": "510046s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which State Possesses biggest coal reserve?",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiggest coal reserve lies in Jharkhand. As most of the Chhota Nagpur Region lies in this state. It comprise of big coal field in Damodar Valley. ",
            "keyString": "716170s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Himalayan region is poor in mineral resources because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  It is made of crystalline rocks ",
            "optionB": "  The displacement of rock strata has disturbed the arrangement of rock and made it complex ",
            "optionC": "  The climatic conditions are not suitable for exploitation of minerals ",
            "optionD": "  The terrain makes exploitation of minerals difficult and very costly due to transport difficulties ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Himalayan region is poor in mineral resources because the displacement of rock strata has disturbed the arrangement of rock and made it complex. ",
            "keyString": "716216s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement (s) regarding India's coal reserves is/are true ?\nI. Over 90% of total reserves are located in the valleys of Son, Damodar, Mahanadi and Godavari\nII. Indian coal reserves are characterised by low ash content and high calorific value\nIII. India has limited prime coking reserves",
            "optionA": "  I only ",
            "optionB": "  I and III ",
            "optionC": "  II and III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statements regarding India's coal reserves that are true are over 90% of total reserves are located in the valleys of Son, Damodar, Mahanadi and Godavari, Indian coal reserves are characterised by low ash content and high calorific value and India has limited prime coking reserves. ",
            "keyString": "716376s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the correct sequence of these areas in descending order of their coal reserves?\n1. Himalayas\n2. Chhotta Nagpur\n3. Chhattisgarh\n4. Son Valley",
            "optionA": "  1, 4, 3, 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2, 4, 3, 1 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3, 4, 2 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 3, 4, 1 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct sequence of these areas in descending order of their coal reserves are Chhotta Nagpur, Chhattisgarh, Son Valley and Himalayas. ",
            "keyString": "716530s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Balaghat is known for its diamond mines.\n2. Majhgawan is known for its manganese deposits.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth the statements are incorrect. Balaghat of Madhya Pradesh is known for its manganese mines. Majhgawan is famous for its diamond mines. ",
            "keyString": "716672s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The deepest mine in Asia is",
            "optionA": "  Jaduguda mine ",
            "optionB": "  Kolar Gold mine ",
            "optionC": "  Suladesi mine ",
            "optionD": "  West Irian mine ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe deepest mine in Asia is Kolar Gold mine. Kolar Gold Fields (KGF) was one of the major gold mines in India and is located in the Kolar district in Karnataka, close to the city of Bangalore. It was closed in 2003 due to reducing deposits and increasing costs. The mine is considered the world's second deepest gold mine.",
            "keyString": "786725s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where in India is mica mined?",
            "optionA": "  Nasirabad (Rajasthan) ",
            "optionB": "  Gaya (Bihar) ",
            "optionC": "  Nellore (Andhra Pradesh) ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn India mica is mined in Nasirabad (Rajasthan), Gaya (Bihar) and Nellore (Andhra Pradesh). ",
            "keyString": "786990s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which State of India has the largest reserves of monazite, with a high thorium content?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKerala has the largest reserves of monazite, with a high thorium content. Monazite is a reddish-brown phosphate mineral containing rare-earth metals. It occurs usually in small isolated crystals. It has a hardness of 5.0 to 5.5 on the Mohs scale of mineral hardness and is relatively dense, about 4.6 to 5.7 g/cm3. ",
            "keyString": "787174s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The plateau rich in minerals in India is",
            "optionA": "  Malwa Plateau ",
            "optionB": "  Chhotanagpur Plateau ",
            "optionC": "  Deccan Plateau ",
            "optionD": "  Mysuru Plateau ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe plateau rich in minerals in India is Chhotanagpur Plateau. Chotanagpur plateau is called the storehouse of minerals due to the fact that it is rich in minerals like mica, bauxite, copper, limestone, iron ore and coal. It is responsible for a significant share of the country's mineral output. ",
            "keyString": "787342s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest coal reserves of India are found in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionB": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe largest coal reserves of India are found in Jharkhand. Jharkhand has the first rank in coal reserves and its production. Most of the coal fields in the state of Jharkhand are located in a narrow belt running in the east-west direction almost along 24% north latitude from the Gondwana period. The main coal mining centres of the state are Auranga, Bokaro, Dhanbad, Jharia, Giridh, Karanpur, Ramgarh and Hutar. ",
            "keyString": "787498s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the biggest reserve of mica?",
            "optionA": "  In South Africa ",
            "optionB": "  In India ",
            "optionC": "  In USA ",
            "optionD": "  In Australia ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiggest reserve of mica is in India. It is in Koderma District of Jharkhand. About 95% of mica reserves in India are located in Jharkhand, Andhra Pradesh & Rajasthan state. ",
            "keyString": "831497s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which central government agency is responsible for the mapping and exploration of minerals?",
            "optionA": "  The Geological Survey of India ",
            "optionB": "  Surveyor General of India ",
            "optionC": "  National Mineral Development Corporation Ltd ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Bureau of Mines ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Geological Survey of India agency is responsible for the mapping and exploration of minerals. Geological Survey of India [GSI], an attached office of the Ministry of Mines, proposes to take up aerogeophysical survey of 8.13 lakh square kilometer of geological potential area in the country through outsourcing. ",
            "keyString": "831528s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first coal mine in India",
            "optionA": "  Dhanbad ",
            "optionB": "  Jharia ",
            "optionC": "  Raniganj ",
            "optionD": "  Asansol ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRaniganj is the first coal mine in India. Coal mining in India first started in the Raniganj Coalfield. In 1774, John Sumner and Suetonius Grant Heatly of the British East India Company found coal near Ethora, presently in Salanpur community development block. ",
            "keyString": "831541s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Coal mines in Jharkhand are located at",
            "optionA": "  Jharia ",
            "optionB": "  Jamshedpur ",
            "optionC": "  Ranchi ",
            "optionD": "  Lohardaga ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoal mines in Jharkhand are located at Jharia. In Jharkhand, Jharia in Dhanbad is the Coal Capital of India apart from this you will find the Coal mines in Girdih, Ramgarh, Dumka and Bokaro. India's largest coalfield is in Raniganj, West Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "831554s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Iron ore mines are located in",
            "optionA": "  Salem, Bhadravati, Raniganj ",
            "optionB": "  Hazaribagh, Jharia, Kudremukh ",
            "optionC": "  Monghyr, Balaghat, Hazaribagh ",
            "optionD": "  Singhbhum, Mayurbhanj, Bastar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIron ore mines are located in Singhbhum, Mayurbhanj and Bastar. ",
            "keyString": "831565s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Panna\" is an important place in Madhya Pradesh. It is famous for",
            "optionA": "  Gold mines ",
            "optionB": "  Silver mines ",
            "optionC": "  Diamond mines ",
            "optionD": "  Iron mines ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPanna is an important diamond mining place in Madhya Pradesh. It lies to the North East of Vindhya Ranges extended to about 240 km known Panna group. ",
            "keyString": "874444s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Talcher is important for which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Cable Industry ",
            "optionB": "  Hydro Power Generation ",
            "optionC": "  Atomic Reactor ",
            "optionD": "  Heavy Water Plant ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHeavy water is used as moderator & coolant in nuclear reactors. Department of Atomic Energy of Government of India has the responsibility to produce for nuclear reactor. One such production plant is in Talcher, Odisha.",
            "keyString": "874657s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following oil refineries of India from west to east:\n1. Koyali\n2. Bongaigaon\n3. Mathura\n4. Haldia",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 3, 4 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 3, 4, 2 ",
            "optionC": "  3, 1, 2, 4 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 4, 3, 1 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following oil refineries of India from west to east are Koyali, Mathura, Haldia and Bongaigaon. ",
            "keyString": "874838s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the most important raw material for generation of power in India?",
            "optionA": "  Mineral Oil ",
            "optionB": "  Natural Gas ",
            "optionC": "  Uranium ",
            "optionD": "  Coal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of the power generation in India happens through thermal power stations in which coal is used majorly as fuel. As most of the coal available in India is of poor quality with low carbon content and there for it's useless for metallurgical processes of metals.",
            "keyString": "875015s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Nathpa Jhakri power Project located?",
            "optionA": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNathpa Jharki Dam has been constructed on Sutiej river in Himachal Pradesh. This project was completed in 2004. ",
            "keyString": "875183s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following minerals are found in a natural way in the State of Chhattisgarh ?\n1. Bauxite\n2. Dolomite\n3. Iron ore\n4. Tin",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 only ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 4 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2, 3 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following minerals that are found in a natural way in the State of Chhattisgarh are Bauxite, Dolomite, Iron ore and Tin. ",
            "keyString": "933133s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tummalapalle, where huge reserves of Uranium have mission in July, 2011, lies in the state of",
            "optionA": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTumallapalle lies in Andhra Pradesh. The Atomic Energy Commission confirmed that it might have world's largest uranium reserves.",
            "keyString": "933347s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Diamond mine are being worked at ________.",
            "optionA": "  Hazaribagh, Jharkhand ",
            "optionB": "  Kolar, Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Neyveli, Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Panna, Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDiamond mine are being worked at Panna, Madhya Pradesh. India have one active diamond mine at Panna, in Madhya Pradesh, which is run by the state-owned National Mineral Development Corporation. ",
            "keyString": "933526s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Singhbhum where copper ore is mined is in",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSinghbhum where copper ore is mined is in Jharkhand. Singhbhum shear zone is known as a mineral rich and potentially economic. ",
            "keyString": "933692s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gold Mines in India are located mainly in",
            "optionA": "  Kolar ",
            "optionB": "  Raniganj ",
            "optionC": "  Jadugoda ",
            "optionD": "  Veeranam ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGold Mines in India are located mainly in Kolar. It had produced tonnes and tonnes of gold. It includes the township of the same name, viz. K.G.F, where reside mainly the families of the employees of Bharat Gold Mines Limited (BGML) and BEML (formerly Bharat Earth Movers Limited). ",
            "keyString": "933856s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest producer of wood pulp is",
            "optionA": "  India ",
            "optionB": "  Canada ",
            "optionC": "  Russia ",
            "optionD": "  USA ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCanada is the largest producer of wood pulp, newsprint paper and other types of paper in the world. This has been possible due to its vast resources of coniferous forest, which provide raw material for paper industry.",
            "keyString": "984894s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a major rubber producing states?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOdisha is not a major rubber producing states. The major crop produced is rice and the state is one of the leading producer of fish. ",
            "keyString": "985118s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following cannot be called a rubber-producing state?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUttar Pradesh cannot be called a rubber-producing state. The state of Uttar Pradesh ranks first in terms of wheat production.",
            "keyString": "985300s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of Indian tea production comes from Assam, West Bengal, Kerala and Tamil Nadu",
            "optionA": "  50 ",
            "optionB": "  75 ",
            "optionC": "  98 ",
            "optionD": "  30 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t98 of Indian tea production comes from Assam, West Bengal, Kerala and Tamil Nadu. ",
            "keyString": "985473s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following oil fields of India is the oldest and still producing oil ?",
            "optionA": "  Bombay High ",
            "optionB": "  Digboi ",
            "optionC": "  Ankleshwar ",
            "optionD": "  Naharkatiya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDigboi oil fields of India is the oldest and still producing oil. Digboi has the distinction of being India's oldest continuously producing oilfield. Digboi refinery, now a division of Indian Oil Corporation, had a capacity of about 0.65 MMTPA as of 2003. The Digboi refinery is the world's oldest oil refinery still in operation. ",
            "keyString": "985641s18m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following places, steel and iron industry was set up with the help of Germany?",
            "optionA": "  Durgapur ",
            "optionB": "  Bhilai ",
            "optionC": "  Rourkela ",
            "optionD": "  Bhadravati ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first integrated steel plant of India of public sector was setup in Rourkela, Odisha with German collaboration. Steel Authority of India operates it. ",
            "keyString": "22451s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following industries is known as 'Sunrise Industry'?",
            "optionA": "  Iron & Steel ",
            "optionB": "  Cotton Textile ",
            "optionC": "  Information Technology ",
            "optionD": "  Tea & Coffee ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSunrise industries are those new industries which have seen rise in their growth and will become important industries of future. One such industry is IT industry. ",
            "keyString": "22982s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vindhyan system of rocks is important for the production of",
            "optionA": "  Precious stones and building materials ",
            "optionB": "  Iron ore and manganese ",
            "optionC": "  Bauxite and mica ",
            "optionD": "  Copper and uranium ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vindhyan system of rocks is important for the production of precious stones and building materials. ",
            "keyString": "88042s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Khetri project in Rajasthan has been set up for producing",
            "optionA": "  Zinc ",
            "optionB": "  Manganese ",
            "optionC": "  Copper ",
            "optionD": "  Salt ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhetri project in Rajasthan has been set up for producing Copper. Hindustan Copper Limited is coming up with Water Treatment Plant Project at Khetri, Jhunjhunu, Rajasthan. ",
            "keyString": "88572s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One-tenth of the total salt produced in India comes from",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu Coast ",
            "optionB": "  Sambhar Lake ",
            "optionC": "  Chilka Lake ",
            "optionD": "  Wular Lake ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne-tenth of the total salt produced in India comes from Sambhar Lake. The world wide salt production is currently 200 million tons and exceeding the mark rapidly. The worldwide industries manufacture this huge quantity of salt not only for consumption but for non-edible and industrial purpose as well. Almost sixty percentage of salt production in the whole world goes to the industrial usage. ",
            "keyString": "89087s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ankaleshwar in India is known for the production of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Bauxite ",
            "optionB": "  Coal ",
            "optionC": "  Iron ore ",
            "optionD": "  Petroleum ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnkaleshwar in India is known for the production of Petroleum. Ankleshwar, also famous as Gujarat's \u201cCity of Oil\u201d is known for its industrial township called Gujarat Industrial Development Corporation (GIDC). This city has over a thousand chemical plants, manufacturing products such as insecticide, pharmaceuticals, paints, and chemicals. ",
            "keyString": "89565s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The state which tops in the production of rubber is",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe state which tops in the production of rubber is Kerala. Kerala accounts for more than 90 per cent of the total rubber production in the country. The total area under rubber cultivation in the state is 5.45 lakh hectares.",
            "keyString": "89934s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements-\n1.NTPC has entered in the area of hydro-power,\n2.Power Grid Corporation has entered in Telecom Industry,\nWhich of the above statement is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNTPC stands for National Thermal Power Corporation. It generates electricity mainly by utilisation of fossil fuels. But, as the reserves of fossil fuels are limited the organisation is building hydroelectric power plants also. On the other hand, Power Grid Corporation is involved in Telecom industry as similar infrastructure can be used there also.",
            "keyString": "174477s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following States enjoys ideal conditions for the development of petrochemical industries?",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGujarat enjoys ideal conditions for the development of petrochemical industries. Gujarat contributes 15% of the total national chemical exports. Petrochemical Industry in Gujarat produces 13.048 Mn Tonnes of petrochemical products and also contributes around 62% to the total production of the country. ",
            "keyString": "175048s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following problems being faced by the Indian Coal Industry :\nI. Poor quality of coal and bottlenecks in the coal movement\nII. Low utilisation capacity of washeries\nIII. Growing dependence on the import of coking coal\nIV. Administered prices",
            "optionA": "  II, III and IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, II, III and IV ",
            "optionC": "  I, III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  I, II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe problems being faced by the Indian Coal Industry are Poor quality of coal and bottlenecks in the coal movement, Low utilisation capacity of washeries, Growing dependence on the import of coking coal and Administered prices. ",
            "keyString": "175582s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following City, Hindustan Machine and Tool Industry is located?",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Bengaluru ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHindustan Machine & Tool Industry is located in Bengaluru, Karnataka. It was founded in 1953 and comes under Ministry of Heavy Industries & Public Enterprises. ",
            "keyString": "176074s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL) is in",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  Bengaluru ",
            "optionD": "  Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL) is an Indian state-owned aerospace and defence company headquartered in Bangalore, India.",
            "keyString": "176316s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Gondwana coal is a laminated, bituminous coal.\n2. Gondwana coal is completely free from moisture, sulphur and phosphorus.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGondwana coal is a laminated, bituminous coal. The Gondwana coal is a laminated bituminous coal within which dull and bright layers alternate. This coal is almost free from moisture but it contains variable quantities of sulphur and phosphorous. In general, Gondwana coal is good steam or gas coal. This is also known as metallurgical coal. ",
            "keyString": "243524s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The total number of refinery working in Assam is/are",
            "optionA": "  One ",
            "optionB": "  Two ",
            "optionC": "  Three ",
            "optionD": "  Four ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDigboi Refinery in 1901, Noonmati in Guwahati in 1962, Dhaligaon near Bongaigaon, 1962 Numaligarh, Golaghat district 1999. ",
            "keyString": "244039s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements are true with respect to iron ore?\nI. Limestone and coal are important for smelting iron ore\nII. More than 20% of the world iron ore deposits are in India\nIII. Odisha and Jharkhand top in the production of iron ore\nIV. Iran is the largest buyer of Indian iron ore",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  II and III ",
            "optionC": "  III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  II, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following statements that are true with respect to iron ore are Limestone and coal are important for smelting iron ore, More than 20% of the world iron ore deposits are in India and Odisha and Jharkhand top in the production of iron ore. ",
            "keyString": "244554s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India is the largest tea producing country in the world. It is grown in which of the following states mainly?",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Haryana ",
            "optionC": "  Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia is the largest tea producing country in the world. It is grown in Assam mainly. Assam produces the largest volume of tea in India. Assam Tea is known for its body, bright color rich flavor and aroma. Tea estates of Assam are world\u2019s largest tea growing region, grown in the lowlands of Assam in the valley of the Brahmaputra river. ",
            "keyString": "245115s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gujarat is the largest producer of salt in India because",
            "optionA": "  It has extensive dry coast ",
            "optionB": "  Its coastal waters are very saline ",
            "optionC": "   It has extensive shallow ",
            "optionD": "  Besides producing salt from saline water, it\nhas reserves of rock salt ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGujarat lies in sub tropical high pressure zone towards west India. It is characterized by semi - arid & arid conditions. The coastal zone of the state remains dry during most part of the year. Hence, salt production is high.",
            "keyString": "246003s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Idukki hydroelectric plant la on the river",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Periyar ",
            "optionD": "  Tungabhadra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Idukki hydroelectric plant is on the river Periyar. It supports a 780 MW hydroelectric power station. It is built on the Periyar River, in the ravine between the Kuravan and Kurathi Hills in Kerala, India.",
            "keyString": "311989s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mahatma Gandhi Hydroelectric Project is on which river?",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Sharavati ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJog Falls is created by the Sharavathi River dropping 253 m (830 ft), making it the second-highest plunge waterfall in India after the Nohkalikai Falls with a drop of 335 m (1100 ft) in Meghalaya. ",
            "keyString": "312571s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India mainly exports iron ore to which country?",
            "optionA": "  Japan ",
            "optionB": "  Bhutan ",
            "optionC": "  Indonesia ",
            "optionD": "  Russia ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia has large reserves of iron ore while Japan is highly industrialised with big automobile industry which requires iron ore. So, India has been exporting iron to Japan since end of second world war. From eastern port of Vizag most of the iron is exported to Japan & other East Asian economies. ",
            "keyString": "313090s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following states is Rosa Power Plant located?",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Odisha ",
            "optionD": "  Haryana ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Rosa Thermal Power Plant is a 1200 MW of coal based generation capacity at Rosa village in Shahjahanpur, Uttar Pradesh.",
            "keyString": "313598s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The construction of Tehri dam is done across which river",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionC": "  Bhagirathi ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTehri Dam built across river Bhagirathi in Tehri, Uttarakhand is a 1000 megawatt power project. It also holds a water reservoir for irrigation municipal water supply. ",
            "keyString": "314053s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Diamond mines are found in",
            "optionA": "  Panna, Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Mysore, Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Waltair, Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Ajmer, Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPanna district of Madhya Pradesh is famous fordiamond mining. It also hastiger reserve known as 'Panna National Park', Diamond Mining Project of National Mineral Development Corporation manages diamond mines in Panna. ",
            "keyString": "379989s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Panna\" is an important place in Madhya Pradesh. It is famous for mines of",
            "optionA": "  Gold ",
            "optionB": "  Silver ",
            "optionC": "  Diamond ",
            "optionD": "  Iron ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPanna district of Madhya Pradesh is famous fordiamond mining. It also hastiger reserve known as 'Panna National Park', Diamond Mining Project of National Mineral Development Corporation manages diamond mines in Panna. ",
            "keyString": "380409s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Iron ore produced from the mines of Kudremukh is exported from which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Marmagao ",
            "optionB": "  Kochin ",
            "optionC": "  Mangalore ",
            "optionD": "  Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIron ore is mined from the hills of Kudremukh in Chikmagaluru District of Karnataka in Western Ghats. From here it is transported to the port of Mangalore in the formslurry through pipeline for exports. ",
            "keyString": "380836s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important uranium mine of India is located at",
            "optionA": "  Manavalakurichi ",
            "optionB": "  Gauribidanur ",
            "optionC": "  Vashi ",
            "optionD": "  Jadugoda ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJadugoda Mines of uranium lies in Purbi Singhbhum district of Jharkhand. It started functioning in 1967 as uranium mine of India.",
            "keyString": "381252s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A prominent break in the continuity of the Sahyadris is",
            "optionA": "  Doda Betta ",
            "optionB": "  Anamudi Peak ",
            "optionC": "  Anaimalai Hills ",
            "optionD": "  Palghat Gap ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA prominent break in the continuity of the Sahyadris is Palghat Gap. Palghat Gap, major break in the Western Ghats mountain range, in southwestern India. Located between the Nilgiri Hills to the north and the Anaimalai Hills to the south, it is about 20 miles (32 km) wide and straddles the Kerala\u2013Tamil Nadu border, serving as a major communication route between those two states. ",
            "keyString": "381437s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is untraditional sources of Energy?",
            "optionA": "   Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Fuel ",
            "optionC": "  Petroleum ",
            "optionD": "   Biogas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoal, petroleum & forest fuel such as wood has been used by humans since ages. They are the direct source of energy hence they were more exploited, whereas biogas is a concept of clean energy. The gas produced from animal &human waste is used in various manners as fuel. Conventional sources were direct fuels whereas biogas is first produced fromorganicwaste & than utilised as fuel. ",
            "keyString": "459074s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Umiam Hydro Power Project Dam is located few kilometres north to which of the following",
            "optionA": "  Kohima ",
            "optionB": "   Imphal ",
            "optionC": "  Guwahati ",
            "optionD": "  Shillong ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUmiam hydro power project is on Umiam lake which is located about 15 kms north of Shillong in Meghalaya state. A dam was created across Umriam river in early in 1960s, to creat this lake.",
            "keyString": "459743s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following city is the centre for manufacturing of Penicillin?",
            "optionA": "  Sindri ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Pimpari ",
            "optionD": "  Alwaye ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPimpari is the suburban metropolis region in Pune, Maharashtra. Hindustan Antibiotics Limited (HAL) is set up there by Government of India to produce Pencillin. ",
            "keyString": "460265s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Mumbai High\" is related to",
            "optionA": "  Iron ",
            "optionB": "  Petroleum ",
            "optionC": "  Tomb ",
            "optionD": "  Jute ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMumbai High also known as Bombay High is an off shore region beyond Mumbai coast from where petroleum is drilled. ",
            "keyString": "460762s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following places in India does not have a nuclear power plant?",
            "optionA": "  Narora ",
            "optionB": "  Rawatbhata ",
            "optionC": "  Silchar ",
            "optionD": "  Tarapore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilchar does not have a nuclear power plant. A nuclear power plant or nuclear power station is a thermal power station in which the heat source is a nuclear reactor. ",
            "keyString": "461166s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not renowned for the manufacture of silk?",
            "optionA": "  Bhagalpur (Bihar) ",
            "optionB": "  Srinagar (Jammu and Kashmir) ",
            "optionC": "  Moradabad (Uttar Pradesh) ",
            "optionD": "  Mysore (Karnataka) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMoradabad (Uttar Pradesh) is not renowned for the manufacture of silk. Moradabad is known as the capital of brass handicraft industry of India. The city features generation of families devoted to brass and glass work. Almost maximum of the city\u2019s population is involved in brass handicraft work. The city is also known as Pital Nagri. It also manufactures silk. ",
            "keyString": "549062s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which shipyard is known for the manufacture of bargets, coasters arid dredgers?",
            "optionA": "  Hindustan Shipyard ",
            "optionB": "  Mazgaon Shipyard ",
            "optionC": "  Garden Reach Shipyard ",
            "optionD": "  Cochin Shipyard ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGarden Reach Shipyard is known for the manufacture of bargets, coasters arid dredgers. It is one of India's leading shipyards, located in Kolkata, West Bengal. It builds and repairs commercial and naval vessels. Presently GRSE has also started building export ships in a mission to expand its business. ",
            "keyString": "549270s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Neyveli Power Project is a ________ Power Project.",
            "optionA": "  Hydro-electric ",
            "optionB": "  Nuclear ",
            "optionC": "  Thermal ",
            "optionD": "  Non-conventional ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNeyveli Power Project is a Thermal Power Project. It consists of two distinct units (Neyveli Thermal Power Station I and Neyveli Thermal Power Station II) capable of producing 1020 MW and 1,970 MW respectively including their expansion units. It is operated by NLC. ",
            "keyString": "549433s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The primary purpose of constructing the Farakka barrage is to ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Preserve and maintain navigation ",
            "optionB": "  Supply drinking water ",
            "optionC": "  Meet the chronic power shortage ",
            "optionD": "  Bring additional areas into irrigation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe primary purpose of constructing the Farakka barrage is to preserve and maintain navigation. The Farakka Barrage Project, constructed in 1975 with the prime objective of preservation of Kolkata Port and for increasing the navigation depth of the Bhagirathi \u2013 Hooghly waterway, has a 2225 m long barrage across Ganga with a canal head regulator to divert 40,000 cusec of water through a feeder canal for inland navigation to maintain Kolkata Port. ",
            "keyString": "549591s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gondwana coalfields are found in",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionD": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGondwana coalfields are found in Madhya Pradesh. Gondwana coal field almost covers all the states of India which reserves coal. Nearly 95% of India's coal is from the Gondwana formation (which is in the Satpuras) and is found in Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Orissa, West Bengal, Maharashtra and Andhra Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "549748s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the first Nuclear Power Plant constructed in India?",
            "optionA": "  Kaiga ",
            "optionB": "  Tarapur ",
            "optionC": "  Narora ",
            "optionD": "  Kota ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst nuclear power station in India is Tarapur nuclear power plant located in Swayam, Maharastra. It is largest nuclear plant of India. It was constructed under 123 Agreecment between India, USA, & IAEA in 1963.",
            "keyString": "662615s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the oldest working 'Refinery'?",
            "optionA": "  Bahamas ",
            "optionB": "  Basra ",
            "optionC": "  Digboi ",
            "optionD": "  Texas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOldest working petroleum refinery is in Digboi, Assam.It was started in the year 1901 by British. It was infact first oil well drilled in Aisa .It is also known as ' Oil City'. ",
            "keyString": "672252s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where are Tapovan and Vishnugarh Hydroelectric Projects located?",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "optionD": "  Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTapovan and Vishnugarh Hydroelectric Projects are located in Uttarakhand. The Tapovan Vishnugad power plant is a 520MW run- of-river project being constructed on Dhauliganga River in Chamoli District of Uttarakhand, India. ",
            "keyString": "672426s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Singhbhum is famous for ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Iron ",
            "optionC": "  Copper ",
            "optionD": "  Both B and C ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSinghbhum is famous for iron and copper. The Singhbhum district has been divided into three smaller districts, being East Singhbhum, West Singhbhum and Saraikela Kharsawan. These three districts are part of Jharkhand state. East Singhbhum is famous for Copper and Uranium mines. Most notable Copper mines are Banalopa, Badia, Pathargora, Dhobni, Kendadih, Rakha and Surda. The greater part of West Singhbhum district is covered with deposits of iron ore and other industrially important minerals including Chromite, Magnetite, Manganese, Kainite, Lime stone, Asbestos and Soap Stone. ",
            "keyString": "673331s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India, there are many coal fields found in",
            "optionA": "  Cauvery Valley ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna Valley ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga Valley ",
            "optionD": "  Damodar Valley ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDamodar river flows through Chhota Nagpur Plateau which has many reserves of coal and most of the coal fields lie in Damodar Valley from Jharkhand to West Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "673384s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a commercial source of energy?",
            "optionA": "  Agricultural waste ",
            "optionB": "  Dried dung ",
            "optionC": "  Sun ",
            "optionD": "  Natural gas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNatural gas occurs along with the belt of other fossil fuels in sedimentary rocks. It is also a good source of clean energy as due to good carbon content it has high calorific value with low residue. ",
            "keyString": "731742s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not commercial source of energy?",
            "optionA": "  Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Petroleum ",
            "optionC": "  Natural Gas ",
            "optionD": "  Firewood ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommercial source of energy such as coal, petroleum & natural gas are obtained commercially whereas fire wood is obtained non-commercially by people from wastelands forestlands in terms of twigs, sticks etc. ",
            "keyString": "731857s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where has the Geological Survey of India located most of India's Chromite?",
            "optionA": "  Cuttack ",
            "optionB": "  Singhbhum ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Hubli ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn India most of chromate deposits (about 93%) are located in Sukinda Vally of Cuttack district in Odisha. ",
            "keyString": "732802s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which one of the following States are Namchik-Namphuk Coalfields located?",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Mizoram ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNamchik-Namphuk coalfields are located in Arunachal Pradesh. the Namchik-Namphuk coalfield was allocated to the Arunachal Pradesh Mineral Development and Trading Corporation Ltd (APMDTCL) on October 28, 2003 by the coal ministry. The total area of the coal block is 133.65 hectares and the mining lease is held by the corporation for a period of 20 years. ",
            "keyString": "732856s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sextant is an instrument used in which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Gynaecology ",
            "optionB": "  Navigation ",
            "optionC": "   Birth control ",
            "optionD": "  Medical treatment ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe angular distances between two visible objects is measured with the help of sextant. Later on this measurement is used for purpose of navigation & surveying. It is primarily used to measure angle between earth's horizon & astronomical objects. ",
            "keyString": "732888s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the source of natural energy of the hot springs at Manikaran in Himachal Pradesh?",
            "optionA": "  Geothermal Energy ",
            "optionB": "  Biomass Energy ",
            "optionC": "  Thermal Energy ",
            "optionD": "  Hydro Energy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGeothermal energy is the heat energy produced within Earth's surface. Sometimes magma from inside come near to Earth surface heating up the rocks at shallow depth. The rocks instead heat the water body which comes in their contact. Similar tendencies prevail in Himachal Pradesh. Here, hot spring is situated near Parbati river spreadingto a distance of 1.3 km. ",
            "keyString": "818476s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The contribution of Hydropower in India's total\npower is almost",
            "optionA": "  Half ",
            "optionB": "  Onethird ",
            "optionC": "  Onefourth ",
            "optionD": "  Onefifth ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn India most of the electricity is produced through thermal power stations where mostly coal is used as raw material. Although, India has a great potential to produce hydroelectricty but still it has not harnessed it properly & only 1/5 of it contributes to total energy consumption. ",
            "keyString": "820879s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Jaitapur, which one of the following power plants is being set up?",
            "optionA": "  Coal based ",
            "optionB": "  Hydro-electric ",
            "optionC": "  Gas based ",
            "optionD": "  Nuclear based ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Jaitapur, nuclear based power plants is being set up. The power project is proposed by Nuclear Power Corporation of India (NPCIL) and would be built at Madban village of Ratnagiri district in Maharashtra. ",
            "keyString": "824057s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rana Pratap Sagar Plant (Rajasthan) is associated with ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Nuclear power ",
            "optionB": "  Solar energy ",
            "optionC": "  Hydroelectricity ",
            "optionD": "  Irrigation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRana Pratap Sagar Plant (Rajasthan) is associated with Hydroelectricity. Rana Pratap Sagar Hydroelectric Power Station India is located at Rawatbhata, Rajasthan, India. Location coordinates are: Latitude = 24.9174, Longitude = 75.5794. This infrastructure is of TYPE Hydro Power Plant with a design capacity of 172 MWe. ",
            "keyString": "824107s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following places, power is generated\nthrough hydro power?",
            "optionA": "  Neyveli ",
            "optionB": "  Annore ",
            "optionC": "  Tuticorin ",
            "optionD": "  Mettur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Neyveli, Annore & Tuticorin electricity is generated through thermal power plants, whereas, in Mettur it is generated through hydroelectric as well as thermal power plant.",
            "keyString": "824501s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tanks are manufactured at",
            "optionA": "  Kanpur ",
            "optionB": "  Chittaranjan ",
            "optionC": "  Perambur ",
            "optionD": "  Avadi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTanks are manufactured at Avadi. The Heavy Vehicles Factory (HVF) is located at Avadi in Chennai in the Indian state of Tamil Nadu. HVF was set up in 1961 by the Ordnance Factories Board, Government of India to manufacture heavy battlefield equipment, including Vijayantas and T-72 tanks. ",
            "keyString": "908256s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  India is the second largest producer of nitrogenous fertilizers in the world ",
            "optionB": "  India is the ninth largest steel producing country in the world ",
            "optionC": "  India is the second largest producer of silk in the world ",
            "optionD": "  India ranks third in the world in coal production ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia ranks 2nd in the world in coal production after China. ",
            "keyString": "909147s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oldest nuclear power plant at Tarapur is located on the border between",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra and Karnataka ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra and Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat and Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe oldest nuclear power plant at Tarapur is located on the border between Maharashtra and Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "909193s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are wrong?\n1. Bhadravati steel plant - not located near coal deposits\n2. First modern steel plant in India - Burnpur\n3. Bokaro and Bhilai steel plants - German collaboration\n4. Durgapur steel plant - British help",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst modern steel plant in India - Bengal.Modern steel making in India began with the setting of first blast furnace of India at Kulti-Burnpur in 1870 and production began in 1874, which was set up by Bengal Iron Works. ",
            "keyString": "909533s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The best quality coal is",
            "optionA": "  Lignite ",
            "optionB": "  Peat ",
            "optionC": "  Bituminous ",
            "optionD": "  Anthracite ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnthracite is the best quality coal available.It has got the highest carbon content (about 90%). It is mostly used in metallurgical processes of metals.",
            "keyString": "910662s19m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following statements regarding India's coal is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  98 percent of reserves of coal in India belongs to Gondwana period ",
            "optionB": "  Unknown amount of coal lies buried under the Ganga alluvium and the Deccan Trap ",
            "optionC": "  Bituminous coal is found in both lower Gondwana rocks and in Tertiary rocks ",
            "optionD": "  Gondwana coal is mainly found in the river valleys of Damodar, Mahanadi and Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBituminous coal is found only in Gondwana rocks. ",
            "keyString": "4293s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The NTPC has decided to set up its first coal-based power plant in which of the following North-Eastern States?",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionD": "  Meghalaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe NTPC has decided to set up its first coal-based power plant in Assam ",
            "keyString": "4861s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these statements is/are correct?\n1. In India, the maximum part of electric energy is generated by the hydroelectric plants.\n2. In India, the maximum part of electric energy is generated by the thermal power plants.\n3. Neyveli Lignite Corporation Ltd. is located in Tamil Nadu.",
            "optionA": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  2 only ",
            "optionD": "  3 only ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statements that are correct are that In India, the maximum part of electric energy is generated by the thermal power plants and Neyveli Lignite Corporation Ltd. is located in Tamil Nadu. ",
            "keyString": "5566s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following states, Teesta Urja hydro-power project is proposed to be set up?",
            "optionA": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeesta Urja hydro-power project is proposed to be set up in Sikkim. Teesta Urja is setting up Teesta Hydro power project, also known as Teesta III, on Teesta River in the northern district of Sikkim. ",
            "keyString": "5614s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Apart from Tamil Nadu, lignite is found in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  U.P. ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tApart from Tamil Nadu, lignite is found in Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "5947s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tehri Hydro Power complex is constructed on which of the following river",
            "optionA": "  Alaknanda ",
            "optionB": "  Mandakini ",
            "optionC": "  Dhauli Ganga ",
            "optionD": "  Bhagirathi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhagirathi originates from Gangotri glacier in Uttar Kashi district of Garhwal region. Tehri Power Project is built on this river. ",
            "keyString": "109182s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the cleanest source of energy?",
            "optionA": "  Biofuel ",
            "optionB": "  Fossil fuel ",
            "optionC": "  Nuclear power ",
            "optionD": "  Wind energy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is the cleanest source of energy since it creates no pollution while moving the turbine to produce electricity whereas all other given sources produce some percentage of pollution. ",
            "keyString": "109678s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Coal is an example of",
            "optionA": "  Igneous rocks ",
            "optionB": "  Sedimentary rocks ",
            "optionC": "  Metamorphic rocks ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoal is an example of Sedimentary rocks. Coal is a biochemical sedimentary rock because coal is formed from organic matter or sediment that comes from biological processes. Coal is typically found near swampy areas, or areas where sediment has little contact with oxygen. Plant matter that dies and settles to the bottom of the swamp will often be processed by bacteria. Bacteria will often take out the oxygen and hydrogen within the substance and leave the carbon. If this substance is buried deep and hardens, it will become coal. ",
            "keyString": "110058s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Farakka Barrage was commissioned to ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Save Kolkata port ",
            "optionB": "  Link North and South Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Supply drinking water to Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Divert water to Bangladesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFarakka Barrage was commissioned to Save Kolkata port. Farakka Barrage constructed by India, about 18 km upstream near Monohorpur, to save Calcutta Port from silting, but in the process causing widespread and devastating effects, especially in southwestern Bangladesh. ",
            "keyString": "110564s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are true with respect to Indian Railways?\nI. It is the larqest public sector undertaking\nII. Indian Railway network is the fourth largest in the world\nIII. Factories at Kapurthala and Perarnbur manufacture passenger coaches\nIV. The narrow guage lines are confined to the hilly areas only",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  II, III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  I, II, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following are true with respect to Indian Railways are It is the larqest public sector undertaking, Indian Railway network is the fourth largest in the world, Factories at Kapurthala and Perarnbur manufacture passenger coaches and The narrow guage lines are confined to the hilly areas only. ",
            "keyString": "110897s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest solar power plant in India is located at",
            "optionA": "  Nagercoil ",
            "optionB": "  Jaisalmer ",
            "optionC": "  Madhapur ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresently, Kamuthy in Tamil Nadu has the largest solar power plant of India with power generating capacity of 648MW.",
            "keyString": "281276s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Hydroelectric Power Plant in India was set up at",
            "optionA": "  Nizam Sagar ",
            "optionB": "   Shivasamudram ",
            "optionC": "  Ramagundam ",
            "optionD": "  Mettur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst hydro electric power plant was set up at Sidrapong Hydel Power Station in Darjeeling and the other one was set up in 1902 on Shivasamudram Falls. ",
            "keyString": "281317s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ankaleshwar and Navagaon are two oil fields in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnkaleshwar and Navagaon are two oil fields in Gujarat. Ankleshwar, also famous as Gujarat's \u201cCity of Oil\u201d is known for its industrial township called Gujarat Industrial Development Corporation (GIDC). This city has over a thousand chemical plants, manufacturing products such as insecticide, pharmaceuticals, paints, and chemicals. ",
            "keyString": "281339s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rourkela steel plant obtains:\nI. hydel power from the Hirakud dam\nII. coking coal from Jharia coalfields\nIII. iron ore from Baba Budan hills",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rourkela steel plant obtains coking coal from Jharia coalfields and iron ore from Baba Budan hills. ",
            "keyString": "281357s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following sequences of the oil refineries of India as they occur from south to north is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Kochi - Mangalore - Mumbai - Koyali ",
            "optionB": "  Koyali - Mumbai - Mangalore - Kochi ",
            "optionC": "  Kochi - Mumbai - Mangalore - Koyali ",
            "optionD": "  Mangalore - Kochi - Mumbai - Koyali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following sequences of the oil refineries of India as they occur from south to north that is correct are Kochi - Mangalore - Mumbai - Koyali. ",
            "keyString": "281375s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the oldest atomic power station?",
            "optionA": "  Kalpakkam ",
            "optionB": "  Tarapur ",
            "optionC": "  Narora ",
            "optionD": "  Kota ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTarapur is the oldest atomic power station. Tarapur Atomic Power Station (T.A.P.S.) was the first nuclear power plant in India. The construction of the plant was started in 1962 and the plant went operational in 1969. The 320 MW Tarapur nuclear power station housed two 160 MW boiling water reactors (BWRs), the first in Asia. ",
            "keyString": "341466s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the highest quality of hard coal?",
            "optionA": "  Anthracite ",
            "optionB": "  Bituminous ",
            "optionC": "   Lignite ",
            "optionD": "  Peat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe highest quality of hard coal is anthracite. ",
            "keyString": "341675s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is false?",
            "optionA": "  Mica is usually found in metamorphic and igneous rocks ",
            "optionB": "  Aluminium has the advantage over iron as it is resistant to corrosion ",
            "optionC": "  Line is mostly used in galvanising iron and steel goods ",
            "optionD": "  Manganese is largely used in making fertilizers ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tManganese is often used by the steel industry in deoxidizing and desulfurizing additives and as an alloying constituent. ",
            "keyString": "341856s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pair is correct in context of thermal power projects?",
            "optionA": "  Korba - Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Ramagundam - Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Talchar - Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Kawas - Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThermal power station in Kawas, Gujarat is gas based power plant, its total installed capacity is 645MW. It is one out of 7 gas-based power station of NTPC (National Thermal Power Corporation). ",
            "keyString": "342029s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Uranium found in Ladakh is an example of which type of resource?",
            "optionA": "  Unnatural resources ",
            "optionB": "  Actual resources ",
            "optionC": "  Potential resources ",
            "optionD": "  Biotic resources ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPotential resources are those resources which at present can't be exploited due to lack of technology, capital, manpower etc. but with advancement of technology these can be harnesed in future. ",
            "keyString": "342197s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first machine made paper was manufactured",
            "optionA": "  In 1870 near Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  In 1903 in Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  In 1910 at Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  After independence ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first machine made paper was manufactured in 1870 near Kolkata. ",
            "keyString": "405446s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Hydro Power Project is not in Tamil Nadu?",
            "optionA": "  Iddukki ",
            "optionB": "  Aliyar ",
            "optionC": "  Periyar ",
            "optionD": "  Kundah ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIddukki is a place in Kerala. It lies in Western Ghats. It is the biggest hydropower project in Kerala. All the other 3 options are of Tamil Nadu. ",
            "keyString": "405909s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Major coal deposits of India occur in",
            "optionA": "  Seams separated by igneous rocks ",
            "optionB": "  Seams separated by sedimentary rocks ",
            "optionC": "  Seams separated by metamorphic rocks ",
            "optionD": "  Open cast mines ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMajor coal deposits of India occur in seams separated by sedimentary rocks. Today, coal formed by these processes is often found layered between other layers of sedimentary rock. Sedimentary rock is formed when sand, silt, clay, and similar materials are packed together under heavy pressure. In some cases, the coal layers may lie at or very near Earth's surface. In other cases, they may be buried thousands of feet underground. Coal seams usually range from no more than 3 to 200 feet (1 to 60 meters) in thickness. ",
            "keyString": "406577s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Talcher Thermal Power Station is in",
            "optionA": "  Odisha ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Meghalaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTalcher power station is a 460-megawatt (MW) coal-fired power station in Odisha, India, which is owned and operated by the National Thermal Power Corporation. ",
            "keyString": "406622s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Satpura Thermal Power Station is in",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSatpura Thermal Power Station is an existing 1,330-megawatt (MW) coal-fired power station in Madhya Pradesh, India. ",
            "keyString": "406930s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was India's first mobile offshore drilling platform?",
            "optionA": "  Sagar Kanya ",
            "optionB": "  Sagar Mata ",
            "optionC": "  Sagar Samrat ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSagar Samrat is a drill-ship, a merchant vessel designed for use in exploratory offshore drilling of new oil and gas wells or for scientific drilling purposes. It was the first rig that drilled the first well offshore in 1974. ",
            "keyString": "454263s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find the odd one",
            "optionA": "  Tarapur ",
            "optionB": "  Trambe ",
            "optionC": "  Kalpakkam ",
            "optionD": "  Narora ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's first nuclear research facility was setup at Trombay (Trambe) namely BARC, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, where as Tarapur, Narora & Kalpakkam are nuclear Power stations. ",
            "keyString": "454317s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following state, fertilizer complex \"Paradip Phosphate Ltd\" is located?",
            "optionA": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "   Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFertilizer complex \"Paradip Phosphate Ltd.\" is locate in Paradip, Odisha. It was founded in year 1981. It imports raw material from Jordan, Indonesia, Saudi Arabia, Tunisia, Morocco & CIS countries.",
            "keyString": "454457s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pairs are correctly matched?\n\n\n\u00a0\nIrrigation Project\n:\nState\n\n\n1\nDamanganga\n:\nGujarat\n\n\n2\nGirna\n:\nMaharashtra\n\n\n3\nPamba\n:\nKerala\n\n",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the following pairs are correctly matched with Irrigation Project State: Damanganga : Gujarat, Girna : Maharashtra, Pamba : Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "454583s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which one of the following rivers is the Omkareshwar Project associated ?",
            "optionA": "  Chambal ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada ",
            "optionC": "  Tapi ",
            "optionD": "  Bhima ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Omkareshwar hydroelectric Project is situated near Omkareshwar Temple in Mandhata Village in Khandwa district of Madhya Pradesh. This hydroelectric project is built over Narmada River. ",
            "keyString": "454719s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following sources has the largest share in power generation in India?",
            "optionA": "  Atomic power ",
            "optionB": "  Thermal power ",
            "optionC": "  Hydro power ",
            "optionD": "  Wind power ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of the electricity produced in India is thermal electricity. It is about 67% (approx). In thermal power station coal,gas & oil (petroleum) are used as fuels. ",
            "keyString": "503607s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among sources of power India has largest of",
            "optionA": "  Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Oil ",
            "optionC": "  Natural gas ",
            "optionD": "  Lignite ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmong sources of power India has largest of Coal. Coal is the largest source of electricity in the world. Coal-fired plants generate 72% of India's electricity.",
            "keyString": "503754s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are true with regard to coal in India?\nI. Coal is found in sedimentary rocks\nII. The best quality of coal is lignite\nIII. The largest and oldest coalfield in India is known as the 'Ruhr of India'.\nIV. The Damodar river valley is popularly known as the Ruhr of India.",
            "optionA": "  I and IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionC": "  I, III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  II, III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following that are true with regard to coal in India are Coal is found in sedimentary rocks, The largest and oldest coalfield in India is known as the 'Ruhr of India' and The Damodar river valley is popularly known as the Ruhr of India. ",
            "keyString": "503870s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which state, the Koyna Hydro-Power Project is located?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKoyna Power Project is a complex hydropower project with 4 dams. One of the dams is built across river Koyna in Satara district in Maharashtra. Hence, gaining its name. ",
            "keyString": "503979s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which state, Salal Hydro Power Project is located?",
            "optionA": "  Haryana ",
            "optionB": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSalal Hydro Power Project is located in Reasi district of Jammu Kashmir on river Chenab. ",
            "keyString": "504081s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Jawar mines of Udaipur are famous for",
            "optionA": "  Marble ",
            "optionB": "  Zinc ",
            "optionC": "  Granite ",
            "optionD": "  Bauxite ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Jawar mines of Udaipur are famous for Zinc. Zawar is a township created by mining company Hindustan Zinc Limited, for extraction of zinc and lead. An 80MW power plant provides electricity for mining zinc and lead from three major mines. ",
            "keyString": "542909s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The reservoir Gobind Sagar is on which river in Punjab?",
            "optionA": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionB": "  Son ",
            "optionC": "  Rihand ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGobind Sagar is a man-made reservoir situated in Bilaspur District of Himachal Pradesh. One of the worlds highest gravity dams, the Bhakra dam rises nearly 225.5 m above its lowest foundations. In October and November, when the water level of the reservoir is high, a series of regattas are also organised by the Tourism and Civil Aviation department.",
            "keyString": "542942s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main mineral found in upper Brahmaputra valley is",
            "optionA": "  Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Iron are ",
            "optionC": "  Petroleum ",
            "optionD": "  Manganese ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMain mineral found in upper Brahmaputra valley is petroleum. British in 1901 started extracting petroleum in Digboi district of Assam. It is oldest petroleum refinery in India. ",
            "keyString": "542958s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a non-metallic mineral?",
            "optionA": "  Bauxite ",
            "optionB": "  Magnesium ",
            "optionC": "  Gypsum ",
            "optionD": "  Manganese ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGypsum is a non-metallic mineral. Non-metallic mineral reserves consist of stone quarries and clay and sand pits; chemical and fertiliser mineral deposits. ",
            "keyString": "542971s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All example of a mineral occurring as layers in sedimentary rocks is",
            "optionA": "  Lignite ",
            "optionB": "  Gold ",
            "optionC": "  Lead ",
            "optionD": "  Tin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll example of a mineral occurring as layers in sedimentary rocks is Lignite. Lignite, often referred to as brown coal, is a soft, brown, combustible, sedimentary rock formed from naturally compressed peat. It is considered the lowest rank of coal due to its relatively low heat content. It has a carbon content around 60-70%.",
            "keyString": "542982s20m30h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}